Hello , Matthew . What are you doing here so late ?
I came to get the books .
I want to study our accounts .
We 've been doing very well lately .
Over 200 paid admissions today .
You call that good Saturday business ?
If you weren 't so stubborn , we 'd be turning them away from here .
Who cares a hang about history in wax ?
There are people in the world who love beauty .
But more who want sensation , shock !
The morbidly curious . Heh , I won 't cater to them .
Their money is as good as anybody else 's .
You should have seen them turning them away at that wax museum
on 23rd Street - the Eden Musée .
The story 's the same at Madame Tussaud 's in London .
- If you 'd only listened to me- - - I know , Matthew .
murder , torture , executions
scare the living daylights out of people . I don 't care for that kind of patronage .
You 're a great artist , a genius sculptor .
But I 'm an ordinary businessman . I want a quick return on my investment .
I 've got $ 20,000 sunk in this historic peep show of yours .
I could use that money to better advantage .
All right , Matthew . All right .
I 've known for some time you wanted to dissolve our partnership .
I think I may be able to accommodate you .
How ?
A friend is bringing Sidney Wallace , the art critic , here tonight to see my work .
Wallace is rich , and I think I might persuade him to buy you out .
Well , that sounds interesting .
I 'll want a profit on my investment .
Yes , Matthew .
I understand .
You leave everything to me , and I promise you it will be- -
That should be they now .
All right , I 'll wait in the office .
I 've heard of Wallace . He has a pot of money .
If he likes your stuff , put a stiff price on it .
- Does Jarrod live in the building ? - Yes , he has a room upstairs .
You 'll like him , Sidney . He speaks your language .
Please come in . I 'm happy to see you , Bruce .
It was such a bad night I was afraid you couldn 't get here .
We were delayed . He had a meeting at Manhattan Gallery .
My friend Sidney Wallace . Professor Jarrod .
- It 's a great pleasure . - For me also .
That 's a title that was bestowed on me when I became an exhibitor .
It has little to do with my real work .
If you 'll come with me , I 'll show you what that work is .
I 'm afraid the visit of such a distinguished critic
may cause my children to become conceited .
To you , they 're wax . But to me , their creator , they live and breathe .
Here we have two great lovers from the past .
Cleopatra , queen of Egypt , and Mark Antony . Their last meeting .
You 'll recall that Antony , believing Cleopatra to be dead
killed himself with his own sword .
When Cleopatra discovered what happened , she quickly followed her lover .
You noticed how cleverly the hair is mounted on the scalp ?
Yes . How do you do that , professor ?
Well , real hair of the proper color and texture
is pressed into the slightly warmed wax with a scalpel
one hair at a time .
Each wave and curl of the subject 's own hair is reproduced .
Here 's President Lincoln and his assassin , John Wilkes Booth
one of my few concessions to the macabre .
That 's the best figure of Booth I 've seen . You almost expect him to speak .
I wonder what he 'd say after all these years .
I 'm sure he 'd rant a bit .
Even after he shot Lincoln and jumped from the President 's box onto the stage
he couldn 't resist turning to the audience and taking a bow .
I found him a very stubborn person .
- Stubborn ? - Unbelievably .
For days I argued with this fellow before I could get him to pose the way I wanted him to .
- You mean , he talked back to you ? - Of course .
It 's not easy to shut an actor 's mouth .
These groups are like dimensional paintings of the old masters .
This is not only a great show
it 's an art exhibit .
That 's what I told you .
Here we have Joan of Arc
a favorite subject of mine .
I can understand . It 's beautifully done .
Thank you .
I 've done her over a dozen times , haven 't I , my dear ? And still she doesn 't complain .
- What was wrong with her ? - There are no authentic portraits available
so sculptors and painters have to work from models .
I 've never found the right one , but I will one of these days .
It 's a shame to race through such an exhibit .
One should have time to really study these figures .
You 're very kind . My creations have some merit , I suspect
but in bringing back to life the lovely Marie Antoinette
I feel I 've done my best work .
Ah , I 've never seen anything so exquisite .
People say they can see my Marie Antoinette breathe
that her breast rises and falls .
Look at her eyes , they follow you wherever you go .
She 's very real to me .
You know , her eyes do follow you .
They 're made of glass , more 's the pity .
The exact size and color of the original .
They 're inserted into the sockets from inside
by way of the hollow neck , before the head is attached to the body .
Forgive me , my dear , for discussing your intimate secrets .
I 'm sorry . I lose myself at times .
Professor , if people knew what you have inside these walls
you couldn 't accommodate the crowds .
What you need here is exploitation , more advertising .
- That 's what I 've been telling him . - Oh , my partner wouldn 't agree .
He 's not happy here .
He wants to invest in something else . Mr. Wallace
would you become a partner in this venture ? Would you buy him out ?
You know , I might take you up on that if my lawyers approve and the price is right .
With your support , I could do wonders . I 'd make any sacrifice .
Unfortunately , I 'm leaving this weekend for Egypt .
I 'm financing some excavations there .
However , I 'll be back in three months , then I 'll discuss- -
You make me very happy .
You intrigue me , professor . I believe we 'd get along together .
- Good night . - Good night .
- And I 'm grateful to you , Bruce . - Oh , it 's all right .
Thank you both for your visit and your encouragement .
- I 'll probably see you in three months . - Good night .
Good night .
Mr. Wallace is a great art critic , my darling . You heard what he said .
Does he make you happy ?
Of course you 'd say that . But I don 't care about success .
The world will acknowledge your beauty .
And you , my friends
Cleopatra , Mark Antony , Lincoln , Joan of Arc , all of you .
How would it suit you to be famous again ?
I know it 'll please you , you conceited devil .
It was like you to get yourself shot down in a burning barn .
Couldn 't do it without a spotlight , could you ?
Do you really hear what they say , Jarrod ?
Of course .
A man has to be a little nuts to be a good showman .
The sooner I 'm out of it , the better .
You 'll be out soon , Matthew .
Mr. Wallace returns from Egypt in three months .
He 'll be ready to talk business then .
- I heard him . That 's no good for me . - But surely you don 't- -
I have a chance to buy in on something .
It 'll pay off in a big way and three months is too late .
What guarantee do I have that he won 't go cold on the deal ?
- Sorry , Matthew . It 's the best I could do . - I can do better .
How would you like to split $ 25,000 with me ?
And you call me crazy ?
You ever thought of what would happen if we had a fire here ?
In the cellar , there are six barrels of wax . Wax has a paraffin base .
It 's highly inflammable . This whole place would go up like a paint factory .
Burn ? Burn all my people ?
- Do you think I 'm a murderer ? - Oh , stop dreaming .
These dummies are insured for $ 25,000 . That 's $ 12,500 for each of us .
You wouldn 't need Wallace . You 'd have enough to begin again .
No , I 'd rather die myself than see my friends destroyed .
I won 't Let you do it , and I 'll kill you if you try .
Don 't be stupid .
All you have to do is to strike a match and the thing is done .
Yes , my friend was a genius .
A great artist .
Only I could understand him .
We were like that , Cathy . Just like that .
- Couldn 't they ever find him after the fire ? - Not a sign of him .
The place burned like a paint fac- - Like a volcano .
He was such an impractical fellow .
But I still loved him .
And had I been there , I might have saved him .
Oh , but you might have gotten burned yourself , Matty .
Yes . Such is life .
No matter how much we lose , we must still go on living .
Was there- - ? Was there any insurance on the wax museum ?
Yes , I- - I had a little difficulty about that .
According to the terms of the partnership agreement
the money was to go to the survivor of the others .
The insurance company insists upon proof of , uh , my partner 's death .
Yes .
Hee , hee . They always want a corpse .
But they settled finally . This afternoon , as a matter of fact .
They didn 't !
Certified check .
I got it cashed . The money is in my safe .
- You know what that means , baby ? - No , what ?
That little trip I was talking to you about ... ?
Ooh , Matty . Heh .
- You 're such a card ! - Ha-ha-ha .
- How much did you get ? - $ 25,000 .
- Where would you like to go ? Atlantic City ?
No . Niagara Falls . We can get the license in Buffalo .
- License ? - Yeah , you know .
Legitimate .
Ah , why not ? It might be fun .
Uh , waiter ? Waiter , my check .
Pull it tighter , Sue .
Pull it tighter .
I want a waist like Anna Held .
If I pull it any tighter , you 're not going to be able to breathe .
Oh . Oh , that 's all right .
I don 't need much breath , anyway .
As my late friend Matty used to say :
" If a girl don 't watch her figure , the men won 't . "
Matty . Wasn 't that the man you were going to marry ?
Yes , but he hung himself instead .
Oh , Matty was such a card .
Where is your new friend gonna take you tonight ?
The Hoffman House for dinner .
And then to Tony Pastor 's for the vaudeville show .
- That sounds like fun . - He 's a free spender , all right .
Little bit older than I like them , but awfully distinguished looking .
Is he nice ?
Oh , awfully nice .
A real gentleman , except when he 's had a couple of drinks in him .
Ah , that 's to be expected .
I 'm moving up- -
Ooh . I 'm moving up in the world , honey .
No girl ever hits the jackpot till after she passes 14th Street .
- Ha , ha , is that how it goes ? - Sure .
Oh . Look at me .
Not too long ago , I was down on Delancey Street .
And tonight I 'll be right up there among the bright lights on 23rd .
Now , when you get up there tonight , don 't drink too much .
Oh , don 't worry , I won 't .
He keeps trying to pour the liquor into me , but I always manage to keep my head .
After all , now that I 'm going regular with a swell
I got social obligations . Ha , ha .
You know how it is when a fella- - Ah , no , of course you don 't know .
You 're not like me , Sue . You never could be .
You got all the brains and all I 've got is
what I got .
You know , I 'm surprised you even talk to me .
That 's such nonsense . You 've been so good to me .
Oh , why not ?
A girl needs a friend when she 's down on her luck .
Holy smoke ! Look at the time . I 've got to hurry .
Did you find a job yet ?
Oh , no , not yet , but they need a hat-check girl at the Silver Slipper
and I 've got an appointment with the manager tonight .
Oh , I know that fellow . Watch out for him .
- But why ? What 's the matter with him ? - Oh , nothing much .
- Long as you know how to duck . - Oh , that kind ?
Yes .
- Did you eat today ? - Uh-huh . I had everything I needed .
To hear you tell it .
Besides , you 're behind in your room rent .
Oh , well , Mrs. Flannigan will wait for me .
Don 't count on that .
The old buzzard almost locked me out once .
There .
If I don 't sizzle him tonight , I might as well give up .
He 's picking me up in a hansom cab .
No trolley for him . He 's real society .
Oh .
Sue , all I 've got is 50 cents . But you take it and buy yourself some dinner .
- Oh , no , Cathy . - Come on .
Mm-mm .
My friend will give me some money tonight . Then I 'll stake you .
I don 't need any mad money .
I never get mad .
Good luck tonight at the Silver Slipper .
- And don 't forget to duck . - Mm-mm !
Toodle-loo .
Just a moment , Miss Allen .
- What are you coming in so quietly for ? - I didn 't want to disturb anybody .
- Did you get the job ? - No .
- Why not ? - I had trouble with the man who runs- -
- Trouble ? - Mrs. Flannigan , you 'll get your money .
Cathy promised to lend me some tonight
when she comes home .
You better get right up there , then . Because she 's home now .
- Couldn 't it wait until tomorrow ? - No , it could not .
If you want to sleep in this house tonight , you get that money .
All right , I 'll try .
Cathy .
Cathy , it 's Sue . Are you there ?
Cathy ?
I tell you , the scream came from up there .
Let 's look into it .
- Usually there 's a policeman at the corner . - That 's why I 'm blowing the whistle .
Oh ! Cabbie ! Cabbie !
Cabbie , cabbie !
- Mrs. Andrews . - Sue .
- What is it , Mother ? - It 's Sue .
Sue . This is a surprise .
I was just thinking about ... .
- Sue ? - What happened to you , dear ?
- What 's wrong ? - Wait a minute . Wait a minute .
What happened , Sue ?
What is it ?
Cathy- -
Cathy Gray , the girl in my rooming house , was murdered tonight .
- What ? - I found her .
The man who killed her was there in the room .
I tried to get away from him .
But he followed me into the street .
No , Scott , no . Please don 't go out there .
It 's all right , darling . Don 't be frightened .
It 's all right now , dear . You 're safe .
Who found the body ?
One of my roomers . A friend of Cathy 's . Sue Allen .
Which one is Miss Allen ?
- She isn 't here . - Where is she ?
I don 't know . We heard her scream .
When we went looking for her , she was gone .
- Are all your roomers in ? - All but Miss Allen .
Mm-hm .
Lieutenant Brennan will want a statement from each one of you .
See that nobody leaves the house .
When I arrived at the rooming house
this girl had been dead for several hours .
The immediate cause of death was strangulation .
The mark of a cord is still on her throat .
My examination indicated she 'd probably been given a drug .
- You were right . - What was it ?
Something to make her sleep , Lieutenant Brennan . Veronal , perhaps .
I 'll know as soon as we hear from the laboratory .
How long would it take for such a drug to work ?
That would depend upon how much it was diluted .
Yes , it was probably given to her in a drink .
That 's how it 's usually done .
- Business is slow tonight . - What ?
- Three suicides and two murders ... . - And a traffic case since 9 : 00 .
The fellow got hit by an automobile .
I didn 't think those things went fast enough to hurt anybody .
Give them time .
They 're getting better every day .
I hope you like it here , honey . It 's the best we 've got .
Hey , what 's the matter with this one ?
You 'll get used to that .
It 's the embalming fluid makes them jump .
That 's one of the suicides . Just like a woman .
They always have to have the last word .
- Why didn 't you report this to the police ? - She 's doing that .
Last night was the time to do it .
- She was in no condition to come here . - This is murder , Mrs. Andrews .
The body of Cathy Gray was stolen from the morgue last night .
No .
Why would anyone want to take Cathy 's body ?
We 're as much in the dark as you are , Miss Allen .
We had a similar case a few weeks back . Matthew Burke .
I read about that .
Yes , and Patterson , a deputy city attorney , disappeared .
We found no trace of him .
We could 've laid our hands on that man that you saw last night .
You know , that 's the strangest description I 've ever heard .
No human being can look like that .
Sure you didn 't imagine it ?
I did see him . Just as I described him to you .
He was incredible , but very real .
And he couldn 't be the same man who took Miss Gray to dinner ?
That 's impossible .
She told me before she went that he was very good-looking .
That 's what the landlady said , it 's a man with gray hair .
No use showing you any suspects , we have nothing that fits that description .
If we did , we 'd have him in the crazy house .
Don 't leave town . Where can we find you ?
27 Lafayette Street .
- Miss Allen will stay in our home . - Make sure of that . She 's our only witness .
That 's all . Thank you .
How do you do ?
I received a letter giving this address and signed Professor Jarrod .
But I know the professor 's dead . Can you tell me who wrote this letter ?
My name is Sidney Wallace .
- Mr. Wallace . - Professor .
It 's so good- -
Forgive me . Shaking hands with me is an unpleasant experience .
My hands are no longer hands . Sit down , please .
This is Igor . He 's a deaf-mute . He 's one of my assistants .
I 'm going to open another wax museum under a different name .
- It startled you , eh , seeing me here ? - That 's an understatement .
- I thought you were dead . - Jarrod is dead . I am a reincarnation .
When I saw your signature , I thought somebody was playing a joke on me .
I still don 't understand how you escaped the fire .
It 's a mystery to me , too , Mr. Wallace .
All I can remember is that I tried to get out of my studio .
- I failed at first , but here I am . - What a frightful experience .
Somehow I made my way to the house of a doctor .
I still have my limbs , though they won 't bear the weight of my body .
As for my hands , they are no use to me now .
As a sculptor , I can 't control them . But they serve for ordinary functions .
But you 're beginning again ?
With the help of my pupils , yes .
I 'm rebuilding my exhibition from the ground up .
I 'm going to give the people what they want :
Sensation , horror , shock .
Send them out in the streets to tell their friends
how wonderful it is to be scared to death .
I 'll show you one of my subjects .
Do you recall the case of Kemmler , the first man to die in the electric chair ?
- Yes . - Igor is working on a model of his head .
He has a strange obsession , this mute of mine .
Every head he models takes on the shape of his own face .
But in this case I humor him , for actually he somewhat resembles Kemmler .
Uh ... .
Crimes of violence will be reproduced in wax
and exhibited while they are still fresh in the public mind .
What do you think of my scheme ?
I think it will succeed , commercially
though it doesn 't sound like you .
Have you turned your back on beauty ?
No .
No , but I can no longer create it .
I never forgot your Marie Antoinette .
Nor have I.
She will be the leading lady of my new exhibition .
- But I must find her first . - Find her ?
A model , I mean .
Yes , there will be beauty , for contrast , if nothing else .
But each subject must be taken from life .
How can I convince my audience they 're alive , if I don 't believe it myself ?
Oh , I have something I think will interest you .
You follow Igor down into the basement .
I have to go my own way .
Here we are . Interesting , isn 't it ?
One of my pupils is about to dip a body into a bath of wax .
- Body ? - Yes .
The bodies are constructed separately
to exact specifications , of reinforced plaster of Paris .
Oh , uh , this is Leon , another one of my pupils .
- Mr. Wallace . - How do you do ?
The wax is melted in the caldron you see above the vat
liquefied and brought to a boiling point
so that it will distribute itself evenly over the body .
The head and hands , tinted by my own secret process
are attached to the body after it is covered with its skin of wax .
Now watch .
I often wondered how that was done .
It 's a method of my own . Crude but adequate .
- Have you found a home for your museum ? - This is it . The building upstairs , I mean .
We 'll continue to use the cellar as a workshop . Cut a door here and there .
But it 's an excellent location , and the building can be leased at the right price .
I have some capital , but I need more . Thirty thousand , at least .
That 's why I 've asked you to come here .
- I 'll think it over . - Good .
She 's about right , now .
Leon , drain out the surplus , and let her cool .
Oh , Leon , open up Number 27 .
Come this way , please .
I told you that I intend to exhibit scenes of violence .
Here is an interesting subject .
A mystery they 're still talking about .
All right , Leon .
I saw that man 's picture in the papers . This is a remarkable likeness .
- But it can 't be a death mask . - No , it 's from memory .
He hanged himself in an elevator shaft .
Come in , ladies and gentlemen . See the House of Wax .
See the Chamber of Horrors .
Here 's three lovely ladies right over here .
Would you like to see Little Egypt ?
Here she is , ladies and gentlemen
Little Egypt , queen of the harem
who danced at the Colombian Exposition in Chicago in 1893 .
Is she wax , or is she flesh and blood ?
See the world in wax , the Hall of Fame .
The Chamber of Horrors .
A cultural exhibition that 'll enlighten you , amaze you ... .
- I think I could do that . - Oh , you couldn 't .
I could , too , if I took my stays off .
Don 't do that . Don 't talk that way .
Watch it , young lady .
Careful , sir .
Keep your head down or I 'll tap you on the chin .
Look out . Duck !
Wow , that 's a becoming hat you 're wearing .
I wonder if I could clip a flower off it .
Hold steady . Don 't move your head .
Or you 'll lose the powder off your nose .
There is someone with a bag of popcorn .
Close your mouth .
It 's the bag I 'm aiming at , not your tonsil .
Here she comes .
Well , look at that , it 's in the bag .
See the lovely centers of ancient times .
Beauties who died in torture a nd on the block .
Visit our Chamber of Horrors
and pass the time with notorious murderers
who killed with the rope , the knife , and the ax .
Thrills , chills , and laughter for a price within the reach of all .
I hope you don 't think I 've gone too far hiring this fellow to bring people in .
- He makes it sound like a sideshow . - Try him for a week or two .
Once we 're established , we won 't need that sort of thing .
He looks like a real man .
You 'd be surprised .
It is a real man . Sorry .
The historic figures I 'm about to show you will be more interesting
when I tell you that their faces were molded from the original death masks
now in the possession of certain European governments .
First , we have Anne Boleyn
second wife of Henry the VIII , and the mother of Queen Elizabeth
with the executioner Henry borrowed from the French king
so that Anne 's head would be cleaved from her body without too much pain .
He was a thoughtful husband , Henry .
It was he who invented the short cut to divorce .
A very bad pun , I 'm afraid .
Here is another scene of historic violence .
Charlotte Corday and Marat
one of the leaders of the French Revolution .
The lady found him taking a bath
and plunged the knife into his heart .
What a shocking thing .
Yes , wasn 't it ? The poor man was dreadfully embarrassed .
The exhibits in this room will be added to
from time to time as various crimes are committed .
You will read about them in your newspaper
and see them enacted here in waxen tableaux .
Oh , by the way , ladies
this is how your ancestor carried his bride across the threshold .
During the French Revolution
a certain doctor invented a labor-saving device
to take the place of a headmen 's ax .
So successful was this machine
at cutting off the heads of the French aristocrats
they named it after its creator .
And here it is , the bloody guillotine .
Oh , dear , I don 't think I can stand it .
Now , Millie , pull yourself together , honey .
Twelve years ago
the electric chair was first used in New York state .
Here we have an authentic reproduction
of the execution of William Kemmler on August 3rd in 1890 .
Kemmler killed without mercy
and 2000 volts sent him to a higher court .
The torture of the rack . In this case
Lady Anne Askew , an English noblewoman accused of treason
is being put to the question .
Needless to say , she admitted she was a traitor .
Who wouldn 't , under that sort of pressure ?
- Oh , dear . - Is it your corset ?
No , it 's my stomach . It turned over .
Mine turned over too .
And now , my friends
we have that jolly old gentleman known as the modern Bluebeard .
Like his namesake , he killed not wisely , but too well
and did away with eight wives .
Oh , Millie !
Smelling salts , ladies ? Help yourself .
Thank you very much .
Next door to him , we have a mystery of more recent date .
Matthew Burke , the stockbroker .
He was found hanged in the elevator shaft of the building where he had his offices .
Was it murder or suicide ?
Only time will tell .
" Foul deeds will rise , though all the world overwhelm them , to men 's eyes . "
Oh , heh . Thank you .
- You like him , Sue ? - He looks like my Uncle Rufus .
They ought to have a policeman like this in the Eden Musée .
- Haven 't you been there ? - No .
From what I see in the papers , this museum is even better .
Anyway , we 'll soon find out .
Scott .
Mr. Wallace .
Sue , I want you to meet my good friend , Mr. Sidney Wallace .
- Miss Sue Allen . - It 's a pleasure .
- I heard you were in town . - You should have looked me up .
I expect great things of Scott . I consider him one of our most promising sculptors .
- Has he been working hard ? - He never knows when to stop .
- Sue 's been posing for me . - Indeed , lovely subject .
- Thank you . - Not a professional model . She 's a guest .
Sue 's mother and mine were great friends .
- Have you been inside ? - Yes .
Is it exciting ?
If anything , too much so .
But I 'm sure it 'll catch on .
Jarrod , the man who owns the place , is a good friend .
You 'll be interested in him , Scott . Let 's go in , shall we ?
- You know , these figures are excellent . - I thought you 'd agree with me .
They 're not only well done but they 're good theater .
- What do you think , Miss Allen ? - I know they are only wax
but they seem so real , just looking at her makes my neck hurt .
Wait till you see the Chamber of Horrors .
I told Jarrod he should have a nurse on duty there .
- You know that he lost the use of his hands . - Oh ?
- Who did these figures ? - His pupils , but he supervised the work .
- His is the mastermind . - Surely knows his anatomy .
Sue , what is it ?
- Sue , are you crying ? - What 's wrong , Miss Allen ?
A dear friend of mine was murdered and I found her .
She means Cathy Gray , the girl whose body was stolen from the morgue .
What made you think of her now ?
That 's her face .
That 's Cathy 's face , Scott . I know every line of it .
I wake up at night and I see it . I can 't get it out of my mind .
Perhaps that 's the reason you see a resemblance in this figure .
- It 's more than a resemblance . - It 's wax , my dear .
I know , I know , but ... .
Why should it be so like Cathy ?
I think I can explain that .
Oh , uh
Miss Allen , Scott Andrews , Mr. Henry Jarrod .
- This is a pleasure . - You see , Miss Allen- -
Yes , I heard what the young lady said .
The figure of Joan of Arc is a traditional exhibit in wax museums .
It was completed just in time for our opening tonight .
You 're right , my dear . It is more than a chance resemblance .
When I create an important figure , I can 't take just any face .
I saw pictures of your Cathy Gray in the newspaper .
Her face fascinated me . And , well , here she is .
Immortalized as the victim of an earlier event .
- Do you really think she 'd mind ? - No , I don 't think she 'd mind .
Cathy loved to " dress up " as she called it . She used to take fancy dresses
and imitate the actresses she saw in the theater .
- I don 't think she 'd mind . - Then I 'm forgiven ?
Well , there 's nothing to forgive .
I just don 't understand how it can seem so real .
That 's the finest compliment I 've ever received . Thank you , my dear .
Did I hear your name correctly , Scott Andrews ?
- Yes , Mr. Jarrod . - The sculptor I 've been telling you about .
Oh , Sidney showed me some photographs of your work .
He was right . You have great promise .
- What are you doing now ? - I 'm doing a head of Miss Allen .
Let me see your hands .
Yes .
Yes , mine were once like that .
How I envy you .
Mr. Andrews .
Would you be interested in some modeling for me , some originals I have in mind ?
Why , yes . I 'd be honored .
Good . Come here tomorrow morning , we 'll make the arrangements .
I think you 'll like it .
Sidney .
- I want you to look at this girl . - With pleasure .
Who does she remind you of ?
I 've been wondering about that .
I haven 't known Miss Allen more than 10 minutes
but there 's something about her face- -
That haunts you as the face of my Marie Antoinette has haunted me .
Marie Antoinette ?
Of course . I should have seen it at once .
A figure in wax . Mr. Jarrod 's greatest work .
More than wax . She lived .
- You mean I look like she did ? - Exactly as she did .
Once in his lifetime , every artist feels the hand of God
and creates something that comes alive .
So it was with my Marie Antoinette . And I loved her .
But she 's gone now . Horribly destroyed .
Perhaps you will help me to bring her back .
You will come to see me again soon ?
I 'd be glad to .
You 'll be welcome at any time , no matter what I 'm doing .
And you , Mr. Andrews , in the morning ?
- I 'll be here , very eager to begin . - Thank you .
It 's been a very exciting day for me and I 'm a little tired .
So if you 'll forgive me , I 'll say good night .
- Oh , uh , Sidney , one moment , please . - Excuse me .
I 'll be right back .
Forget about it , Sue . You heard what Mr. Jarrod said .
Cathy 's face was inspiration . It 's a portrait in wax .
Why should it seem so real ?
I hate to drag you away , Scott .
Oh , that 's all right . I 'm gonna work here . We 'll see it all another time .
Yes , another time .
Still time to see the entire exhibition .
Get your tickets from the charming lady
in the box office and go right in .
See the world in wax and improve your mind .
See the Chamber of Horrors
and scare yourself out of a year 's growth .
Not again .
What happened , Sue ? Why did you scream ?
I saw Cathy again .
And the man who killed her was right in this room .
I must have been dreaming .
Of course you were , dear .
A lager for the gentleman .
Sarsaparilla for the lady .
- And two knockwurst on rye . - Thank you .
- Enjoying yourself ? - It 's exciting .
- Do nice people come here ? - Ha , ha . Of course .
- These Sunday matinees are very popular . - I don 't know .
It doesn 't seem proper , all those girls showing their ... .
- Their talents . - Heh .
You never saw a show like this in Provincetown ?
- No . - Heh . Don 't worry , your reputation is safe .
You 've been going around with the weight of the world on your shoulders .
Worrying about wax figures and seeing monsters in your dreams .
You need something like this to bring you back to normalcy .
Sue .
- Scott . - Hmm ?
Remember Mr. Jarrod said he first saw Cathy 's picture in the newspaper ?
Yes . What 's wrong with that ?
I knew her so well .
I knew every little expression and they 're all there .
Well , they would be . The man 's an artist .
There 's something else I saw that night in the museum .
Cathy had a habit of wearing an earring in her right ear .
She had the lobe of her right ear only pierced for that .
Well , that 's there too .
How could he see that in a photograph ?
- How can he make it so real unless ... . - What ?
Unless it is Cathy .
Sue . Now , look , I 'm gonna take you to Lieutenant Brennan 's office tomorrow .
I want you to tell him exactly what you 've told me here now .
He 's a policeman , he knows .
He 'll convince you once and for all that no such thing could happen .
Now , relax , honey , and enjoy the show .
I know it sounds fantastic , but you asked me to tell you everything .
You can see this idea 's become an obsession , an unhealthy one , if you ask me .
- You say Jarrod 's a cripple ? - He uses a wheelchair .
He can walk with crutches , but , uh , not very well .
Such a man came and asked to see police photographs of Cathy Gray .
You see , that 's how it 's done . Every detail is studied to make the features true to life .
But why should Joan of Arc have her right ear pierced ?
- Why not ? They wore them then . - Two , not one .
I don 't know , lieutenant , it 's not a suspicion . It 's more a kind of fear , an intuition .
Well , intuition isn 't much help in police work . Facts are what we need .
Suppose you forget about it , and let us do the worrying , eh ?
You mean you 'll investigate it ?
- Of course he does . - Yes , that 's what I mean .
- You both think I 'm crazy . - Oh , we think nothing of the kind .
It was very good of you to listen and be so patient . Thank you .
- Goodbye . - Goodbye .
Thanks .
This is Brennan speaking . Give me Shane .
Hello , Jim . I want you to go to the City License Bureau
and check up on a man named Henry Jarrod .
Yes , he opened a museum on 29th Street , near Broadway .
Yes , The House of Wax .
Dig up all you can . Get a list of his employees and check with me here .
Right .
That 's a copy of her face , all right .
She didn 't look like that the night we saw her in the rooming house .
- Not so composed . - No . Poor kid .
Hey , you know , this fellow Jarrod 's good .
You don 't think Miss Allen 's fears are justified ?
Why , heck , no . Do you ?
That 's wax , how could it be anything else ?
Leave it to a skirt to dream up a crazy idea like that .
So you did come to see me , my Marie Antoinette ?
Or was it that you came to see ?
Mr. Jarrod , I 'm so sorry .
I know I 'm not supposed to touch the figures .
But you couldn 't help yourself . Don 't let it trouble you .
Oh , I beg your pardon , this is Leon Averill and Igor .
How do you do ?
Igor isn 't impolite . He simply can 't talk .
Leon is an artist in his own right .
It was he who did the waxwork on the figure of Joan of Arc .
- Does she still seem real to you ? - As life itself .
Of course , her hair is different , but that doesn 't change her face .
What puzzles me is how you can get such detail from a photo .
Was Cathy wearing her earrings when the police photographed her ?
Earrings ? I don 't remember . Was she , Leon ?
No . No . I don 't think so .
The police would remove the jewelry from the body , wouldn 't they ?
Yet you were careful to show that both her ears had been pierced for them .
Ha-ha-ha . Yes , of course .
If I missed a detail of that sort , Mr. Jarrod would be most displeased .
He insists on reality .
I can understand that .
Oh , just a moment , Leon .
There 's something in this box I think would interest you . Open it , Leon .
Your Mr. Andrews permitted us to make a cast of the head he did of you .
Leon has just finished it in wax . Do you like it ?
It 's sort of a shock to see your head detached that way .
I guess it 's a very good likeness .
Yes , and no .
Andrews is clever , but like all modern sculptors
he has too much imagination . He would improve on nature .
What I need for my Marie Antoinette is you .
The real you .
Nothing less will satisfy me .
Will you come to see me again , my dear ?
Hey , Burke .
You know this fellow Jarrod 's quicker at finding these guys than we are ?
That 's what he says in his advertising .
Look at that . Even the twist in the neck .
That 's a case that gets me . Where is Burke ? Who got him ?
- Who 'd want him ? - We better find out pretty quick .
- You read the blast in this morning 's World ? - Yeah , it 's dynamite .
Chief had me in his office this morning .
If I 'm not careful , I 'll be pounding a beat in the Bronx .
Come here , Jim .
You remember Wilbur Patterson , the deputy city attorney who disappeared ?
Sure .
Does Booth look like Wilbur , or am I crazy ?
Hey , he does a tad with the brush off his lip .
Hair 's different , of course , but the features are something like Patterson 's .
Maybe he looked like Booth . I 've seen dummies that look like people I know .
The caveman is a spitting image of the new commissioner .
Please .
Don 't touch the exhibits .
- Can 't you read the sign ? - I 'm sorry .
Hey , look , where 'd you get the face for this guy that shot Lincoln ?
- From photographs . - Yeah , they take them at that time ?
If you go to the City Library
you 'll find a volume of Mathew Brady 's photos taken during the Civil War .
- Do you work here ? - Yeah .
You make these things ?
Some of them .
What 's your name ?
Leon Averill . What 's yours ?
Jim Shane . I 'm an engineer on the 9th Avenue El .
- It was nice meeting you . - Hm .
Tom , you know me . I 'm no good at names , but I don 't forget faces .
If I can take the muff off of that one , I might be able to place it .
It was a long time ago .
- Mr. Wallace ? - Yes .
I 'm Lieutenant Brennan . Sergeant Shane .
- Glad to know you . Thank you . - Won 't you sit down ?
- Sorry I kept you waiting . - That 's all right .
This is the first time I 've been asked to come to Police Headquarters .
- What am I suspected on ? - Nothing . We thought perhaps ...
- ... you might be able to help us . - Glad to .
We found out that your partner is the same Professor Jarrod
whose museum on 24th Street burned down some time ago .
- That 's true . - Heh .
This , uh , Professor Jarrod was supposed to have been killed in the fire .
Apparently , a slight mistake .
You suspect him of some criminal act ?
- We haven 't a thing on the guy . - We 're curious .
So is the insurance company .
What do you know about his employees ?
There 's Scott Andrews , a protégé of mine .
Yes , we know of him .
Then there 's Igor , deaf-mute , and Leon Averill , who does the wax work .
Averill 's an odd character . Periodical drunkard , but a fine artist .
I 've seen some of his sketches . One of the Savior with his disciples .
Beautiful work .
I 'm afraid I haven 't been much help .
You never can tell . Thank you very much .
- I prefer you not mention this to your partner . - I won 't .
You know , I gamble on Jarrod .
He 's strange , unpredictable , but I think he 's a man of integrity .
- I 'm sure of it . Thank you very much . - Not at all . Good day , gentlemen .
Tom , I told you I knew the man with the whiskers .
Remember that artist in Sing Sing
who painted the Last Supper on the wall of his cell ?
Hendricks . They called him a genius and gave him a parole . Ha , ha !
Yeah , but when they turned him loose , he became a drunk .
He broke parole about a year ago . We 've had him on the wanted list since .
- Carl Hendricks ? - That 's him . Alias Leon Averill .
- Bring him in . - Can do .
Little more bitterness in that face , my boy .
Remember , this fellow has been badly used by the world
and he despises all the people in it .
Deepen those lines around the corner of the mouth .
Not too much .
There . There , that 's better .
What I wouldn 't give to have those fingers of yours .
Thank you , Mr. Jarrod .
Sorry I 've kept you so late here tonight , Scott .
Oh , that 's all right .
Miss Allen is meeting me here .
It 's her birthday . We 're going to celebrate at Chiles ' .
Charming creature .
I was worried about her . The shock of finding that murdered girl ...
- ... gave her some strange ideas . - Yes , I know .
I took her to Brennan at Police Headquarters .
- He set her right . - That 's very good now . Excellent .
Oh , Scott , before you go , would you mind running over to Metzgers for me ?
- Metzgers ? - The place where they make ...
- ... the artificial flowers . - Oh , yes .
They 're doing a background for this new group . Take a look at it for me .
You know what I want . Advise them on the color scheme .
I 'd go myself , but it 's so hard for me to get about .
I know . I 'll be glad to do it . I 'll go right now .
Thank you very much .
I followed him through his bender .
Sometimes , guy gets the shakes so bad , you expect to see his teeth fall out .
- This all he had on him ? - That 's it .
No money ?
Gold .
" To Wilbur Patter- -
Patterson .
With affection and admiration .
City Attorney 's Office . December 25 , 1900 . "
Where did you get this ?
- I found it . - Where ?
- On the El . - What line ?
- Third Avenue , downtown . - When ?
I don 't remember , it was months ago .
- Book him on suspicion of murder . - No . I found that .
I never knew the man who owned it . I never saw him .
Lock him up .
Please don 't put me in a cell . I 'm sick .
Can 't you see my nerves are all shattered ? Look .
Look , please give me one little ... .
Could I have one little drink- - ?
You 're not gonna get anything until you tell us where you got this watch .
- Take him out . - Let 's go .
Scott .
You shouldn 't have done that , my dear .
It is Cathy .
It 's Cathy 's body under the wax .
I knew it . I knew it all the time .
Everything I ever loved has been taken away from me .
Not you , my Marie Antoinette , for I will give you eternal life .
This is where I re-created my Joan of Arc .
It 's an interesting process .
If you have patience with me , my dear , I 'll show you how it 's done .
Can 't stand it .
All right .
All right , I 'll tell you what I know .
Patterson was killed because he looked like Booth .
You killed him .
No , not I. Jarrod , at the waxworks .
His hands were no good . He had to take subjects from life .
You helped him ?
No , they were already dead .
What about Burke ?
He 's there too . In wax .
He was the one who set fire to the old museum .
Jarrod came out of it alive , but insane .
- Cathy Gray ? - Joan of Arc . Joan of Arc ! That 's Cathy .
She 's there with all the rest of them . The whole place is a morgue .
He 'll do the same with Sue Allen , if he gets his hands on her .
You 've got to stop him .
You 've got to stop him before he does any more killing .
That look of horror spoils your lovely face .
What if it should show , even through the wax ?
Sue ?
Sue , are you in there ?
Where 's Sue ?
Where is she ? Where is she ?
The end will come quickly , my love .
There 's a pain beyond pain
an agony so intense , it shocks the mind into instant oblivion .
We 'll find immortality together
for they 'll remember me through you .
Where 's Jarrod ?
Where 's Jarrod ? Where 's Jarrod ?
Andrews , where 's Jarrod ?
In the cellar . He 's got Sue .
Take care of him .
The People 's Exhibit Number One .
You almost lost your head , Miss Allen .
Would you care to keep that one as a spare ?
- No , thank you . - Ha-ha-ha .
We 'll never forget you and your men . Thanks to you , we 're still alive .
But every time I shave , I can still feel that guillotine blade .
- Please , let 's not talk about it anymore . - Yes , you 're right .
Mr. Brennan
thank you for the , uh , use of your coat .
Oh ! Oh , that was nothing .
Well , it meant a lot to me .
Well , when I found you weren 't dressed too warmly , I , uh ...
Well , I didn 't want you to catch a cold .
Goodbye , Mr. Brennan , and thanks for everything .
Bye .
Bless you , Mr. Shane .
Thank you , Miss Allen .
You know , Shane , by the time this guy gets out of Sing Sing
this head will grow a long beard .